<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?><!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd"><metadata>
<idinfo>
<citation>
<citeinfo>
<origin>NOAA Coastal Services Center</origin>
<pubdate></pubdate>
<title></title>
<geoform>Map</geoform>
<onlink>http://www.csc.noaa.gov/crs</onlink>
</citeinfo>
</citation>
<descript>
<abstract>The NOAA Coastal Services Center has developed the Nonpoint-Source 
      Pollution and Erosion Comparison Tool (N-SPECT) to examine the 
      relationships between land cover, soil characteristics, topography, and 
      precipitation regimes in order to assess spatio-temporal patterns of 
      surface water runoff processes, nonpoint source pollution, and erosion. 
      N-SPECT is a GIS tool implemented in Environmental Systems Research 
      Institute's (ESRI®) ArcMap version 8.x / 9.x software package, and requires the 
      Spatial Analyst extension.  Spatial elevation data are used to calculate 
      flow direction and flow accumulation throughout a watershed.  Land cover, 
      soils, and precipitation data sets are processed to estimate runoff volume 
      at both the local (pixel) and watershed scales.  Coefficients representing 
      the contribution of each land cover class to the expected pollutant load 
      are applied to land cover data sets to approximate total pollutant loads. 
      These coefficients were derived from a combination of relevant studies and 
      local water quality sampling data.  Sediment loads are also estimated.  An 
      overall water quality rating is assigned by comparing the total pollutant 
      and sediment loads calculated by N-SPECT to local water quality standards. 
      This water quality rating can help resource managers make informed 
      decisions about water quality and which areas to target for improvement. 
      N-SPECT also provides functionality to compare current land cover 
      conditions to proposed changes in both land use and land cover.  Tool 
      results can be used to help understand and predict the impacts of 
      management decisions on water quality and, potentially, on nearshore 
      environmental health.  N-SPECT is designed to be portable to any 
      watershed, provided the user has access to the necessary data.  Data 
      provided with N-SPECT are for the Wai'anae ahupua'a, the original study 
      area located on the western side of Oahu, Hawaii.  The Wai'anae ahupua'a 
      is the collection of catchments that drain the Wai'anae mountains westward 
      to the Wai'anae coast (west coast of Oahu, HI), including Kaluakauila, 
      Makua, Keaau, Makaha, Kaupuni, Kamaileunu, Mailiili, Ulehawa, and 
      Nanakuli.  The data output covered by this record are listed below in the 
      Supplemental Information section.</abstract>
<purpose>These data are the result of an examination of the relationships between 
      land cover, soil characteristics, topography, and precipitation regimes in 
      order to assess spatio-temporal patterns of surface water runoff 
      processes, nonpoint source pollution, and erosion.  These output data are 
      meant to be used as screening tools for further research.</purpose>
<supplinf></supplinf>
</descript>
<timeperd>
<timeinfo>
<sngdate>
<caldate>unknown</caldate>
</sngdate>
</timeinfo>
<current>publication date</current>
</timeperd>
<status>
<progress>Complete</progress>
<update>None planned</update>
</status>
<spdom>
<bounding>
<westbc></westbc>
<eastbc></eastbc>
<northbc></northbc>
<southbc></southbc>
</bounding>
</spdom>
<keywords>
<theme>
<themekt>None</themekt>
<themekey>N-SPECT</themekey>
<themekey>Nonpoint-Source Pollution</themekey>
</theme>
<place>
<placekt>None</placekt>
<placekey>USA</placekey>
<placekey>Hawaii</placekey>
<placekey>Coastal Zone</placekey>
<placekey>Oahu</placekey>
<placekey>Wai'anae</placekey>
</place>
</keywords>
<accconst>None</accconst>
<useconst>Data set is not for use in litigation.  While efforts have been
made to ensure that these data are accurate and reliable within
the state of the art, NOAA, cannot assume liability for any
damages, or misrepresentations, caused by any inaccuracies in the
data, or as a result of the data to be used on a particular
system. NOAA makes no warranty, expressed or implied, nor does the
fact of distribution constitute such a warranty.</useconst>
</idinfo>
<dataqual>
<logic>None</logic>
<complete>None</complete>
<lineage>
<procstep>
<procdesc></procdesc>
<procdate></procdate>
</procstep>
</lineage>
</dataqual>
<spdoinfo>
<direct>Raster</direct>
</spdoinfo>
<spref>
<horizsys>
<planar>
<gridsys>
<gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
<utm>
<utmzone>4</utmzone>
<transmer>
<sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
<longcm>-159.000000</longcm>
<latprjo>0.000000</latprjo>
<feast>500000.000000</feast>
<fnorth>0.000000</fnorth>
</transmer>
</utm>
</gridsys>
<planci>
<plance>Row and column</plance>
<coordrep>
<absres>30.000000</absres>
<ordres>30.000000</ordres>
</coordrep>
<plandu>Meters</plandu>
</planci>
</planar>
<geodetic>
<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
<ellips>GRS 80</ellips>
<semiaxis>6378137.0000000</semiaxis>
<denflat>298.26</denflat>
</geodetic>
</horizsys>
</spref>
<metainfo>
<metd></metd>
<metc>
<cntinfo>
<cntorgp>
<cntorg>NOAA Coastal Services Center</cntorg>
</cntorgp>
<cntpos>N-SPECT Metadata Manager</cntpos>
<cntaddr>
<addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
<address>2234 S Hobson Ave.</address>
<city>Charleston</city>
<state>SC</state>
<postal>29405</postal>
<country>USA</country>
</cntaddr>
<cntvoice>843-740-1200</cntvoice>
<cntfax>843-740-1224</cntfax>
<cntemail>csc@csc.noaa.gov</cntemail>
<hours>Monday to Friday, 8 a.m. to 5 p.m., Eastern Standard Time.</hours>
</cntinfo>
</metc>
<metstdn>FGDC CSDGM</metstdn>
<metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
</metainfo>
</metadata>
